<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" ".//reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<!-- WK: Set category, IPR, docName -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-dnsop-alt-tld-05" ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes"?>

  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <!-- WK: Set long title. -->

    <title abbrev="Reserve ALT TLD">The ALT Special Use Top Level
    Domain</title>

    <author fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W." surname="Kumari">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>

          <city>Mountain View, CA</city>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Andrew Sullivan" initials="A." surname="Sullivan">
      <organization>Dyn</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>150 Dow Street</street>

          <city>Manchester, NH</city>

          <code>03101</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>asullivan@dyn.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="3" month="June" year="2016"/>

    <area>template</area>

    <workgroup>dnsop</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document reserves a string (ALT) to be used as a TLD label in
      non-DNS contexts or for names that have no meaning in a global context.
      It also provides advice and guidance to developers developing alternate
      namespaces.</t>

      <t>[ Ed note: This document lives in GitHub at:
      https://github.com/wkumari/draft-wkumari-dnsop-alt-tld . Issues and pull
      requests happily accepted. ]</t>

      <t>[ Question for Working Group. It has been proposed that the string
      .ALT should be replaced with something else e.g. .NOT-DNS. As naming
      discussions in the IETF are always short, simple, and not controversial,
      we figured we should open these for discussion now. We would appreciate
      clear feedback on preference and rationale. ]</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Many protocols and systems need to name entities. Names that look
      like DNS names (a series of labels separated with dots) have become
      common, even in systems that are not part of the global DNS administered
      by IANA.</t>

      <t>This document provides a solution that may, in many cases, be more
      appropriate than <xref target="RFC6761"/>.</t>

      <t>This document reserves the label "ALT" (short for "Alternate") as a
      Special Use Domain (<xref target="RFC6761"/>). This label is intended to
      be used as the final (rightmost) label to signify that the name is not
      rooted in the DNS, and that normal registration and lookup rules do not
      apply.</t>

      <!-- Paul Hoffman removed "(apart from the zero-length terminating label)" here because 
     the rest of the sentence says that the domain is not rooted in the DNS. -->

      <section title="Requirements notation">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Terminology">
        <t>This document assumes familiarity with DNS terms and concepts.
        Please see <xref target="RFC1034"/> for background and concepts, and
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-terminology"/> for terminology.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>DNS name: Domain names that are intended to be used with DNS
            resolution, either in the global DNS or in some other context</t>

            <t>DNS context: The namespace anchored at the globally-unique DNS
            root. This is the namespace or context that "normal" DNS uses.</t>

            <t>non-DNS context: Any other (alternate) namespace.</t>

            <t>pseudo-TLD: A label that appears in a fully-qualified domain
            name in the position of a TLD, but which is not registered in the
            global DNS.</t>

            <t>TLD: The last visible label in either a fully-qualified domain
            name or a name that is qualified relative to the root. See the
            discussion in <xref target="background"/>.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="background" title="Background">
      <t>The DNS data model is based on a tree structure, and has a single
      root. Conventionally, a name immediately beneath the root is called a
      "Top Level Domain" or "TLD". TLDs usually delegate portions of their
      namespace to others, who may then delegate further. The hierarchical,
      distributed and caching nature of the DNS has made it the primary
      resolution system on the Internet.</t>

      <t>Domain names are terminated by a zero-length label, so the root label
      is normally invisible. Truly fully-qualified names indicate the root
      label explicitly, thus: "an.example.tld.". Most of the time, names are
      written implicitly relative to the root, thus: "an.example.tld". In both
      of these cases, the TLD is the last label that is visible in
      presentation format -- in this example, the string "tld". (This little
      bit of pedantry is here because, in different contexts, people can use
      the term "fully-qualified domain name" to refer to either of these
      uses.) It is worth noting that the root label is present in the on-wire
      format of fully-qualified domain names, even if not displayed in the
      presentation form.</t>

      <t>The success of the DNS makes it a natural starting point for systems
      that need to name entities in a non-DNS context, or that have no unique
      meaning in a global context. These name resolutions, therefore, occur in
      a namespace distinct from the DNS.</t>

      <t>In many cases, these systems build a DNS-style tree parallel to, but
      separate from, the global DNS. They often use a pseudo-TLD to cause
      resolution in the alternate namespace, using browser plugins, shims in
      the name resolution process, or simply applications that perform special
      handling of this particular alternate namespace.</t>

      <t>In many cases, the creators of these alternate namespaces have chosen
      a convenient or descriptive string and started using it. These new
      strings are "alternate" strings and are not registered anywhere or part
      of the DNS. However they appear to users and to some applications to be
      TLDs. Issues may arise if they are looked up in the DNS. These
      include:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>User confusion: If someone emails a link of the form
          foo.bar.pseudo-TLD to someone who does not have the necessary
          software to resolve names in the pseudo-TLD namespace, the name will
          not resolve and the user may become confused.</t>

          <t>Excess traffic hitting the DNS root: Lookups leak out of the
          pseudo-TLD namespace and end up hitting the DNS root
          nameservers.</t>

          <t>Collisions: If the pseudo-TLD is eventually delegated from the
          root zone, the lookup behavior will change in a non-deterministic
          fashion.</t>

          <t>Lack of success for the user's original goal.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>An alternate name resolution system might be specifically designed to
      provide confidentiality of the looked up name, and to provide a
      distributed and censorship-resistant namespace. This goal would
      necessarily be defeated if the queries leak into the DNS, because the
      attempt to look up the name would be visible at least to the operators
      of root name servers and to any entity viewing the DNS lookups going to
      the root nameservers.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="The ALT namespace">
      <t>In order to avoid the above issues, we reserve the ALT label. Unless
      the name desired is globally unique, has meaning on the global context
      and is delegated in the DNS, it should be considered an alternate
      namespace, and follow the ALT label scheme outlined below. The ALT label
      MAY be used in any domain name as a pseudo-TLD to signify that this is
      an alternate (non-DNS) namespace.</t>

      <t>Alternate namespaces should differentiate themselves from other
      alternate namespaces by choosing a name and using it in the label
      position just before the pseudo-TLD (ALT). For example, a group wishing
      to create a namespace for Friends Of Olaf might choose the string "foo"
      and use any set of labels under foo.alt.</t>

      <t>As they are in an alternate namespace, they have no significance in
      the regular DNS context and so should not be looked up in the DNS
      context. Some of these requests will inevitably leak into the DNS
      context (for example, because clicks on a link in a browser that does
      not have a extension installed that implements the alternate namespace
      resolution), and so the ALT TLD has been added to the "Locally Served
      DNS Zones" <xref target="RFC6303">(</xref>) registry to limit how far
      these flow.</t>

      <t>Groups wishing to create new alternate namespaces SHOULD create their
      alternate namespace under a label that names their namespace, and under
      the ALT label. They SHOULD choose a label that they expect to be unique
      and, ideally, descriptive. There is no IANA controlled registry for
      names under the ALT TLD - it is an unmanaged namespace, and developers
      are responsible for dealing with any collisions that may occur under
      .alt. Informal lists of namespaces under .alt may appear to assist the
      developer community.</t>

      <t>[Editor note (to be removed before publication): There was
      significant discussion on an IANA registry for the ALT namespace -
      please consult the lists for full thread, but the consensus seems to be
      that it would be better for the IETF / IANA to not administer a registry
      for this. It is expected one or more unofficial lists will be created
      where people can list the strings that they are using. ]</t>

      <t>Currently deployed projects and protocols that are using pseudo-TLDs
      may decide to move under the ALT TLD, but this is not a requirement.
      Rather, the ALT TLD is being reserved so that current and future
      projects of a similar nature have a designated place to create alternate
      resolution namespaces that will not conflict with the regular DNS
      context.</t>

      <section title="Choice of the ALT Name">
        <t>A number of names other than "ALT" were considered and discarded.
        In order for this technique to be effective the names need to continue
        to follow both the DNS format and conventions (a prime consideration
        for alternate name formats is that they can be entered in places that
        normally take DNS context names); this rules out using suffixes that
        do not follow the usual letter, digit, and hyphen label
        convention.</t>

        <t>Another proposal was that the ALT TLD instead be a reservation
        under .arpa. This was considered, but rejected for several reasons,
        including:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>We wished this to make it clear that this is not in the DNS
            context, and .arpa clearly is.</t>

            <t>The use of the string .alt is intended to evoke the alt.*
            hierarchy in Usenet.</t>

            <t>We wanted the string to be short and easily used.</t>

            <t>A name underneath .arpa would consume at least five additional
            octets of the total 255 octets available in domain names, which
            could put pressure on applications that need long
            machine-generated names.</t>

            <t>We are suggesting that the string "ALT" get special treatment
            in resolvers, and shim software. We are concerned that using
            subdomains of an existing TLD (like .arpa) might end up with bad
            implementations misconfiguring / overriding the TLD itself and
            breaking .arpa.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>There is a concern that if there were placed under .arpa,
        inexperienced nameserver operators may inadvertently cover .arpa. A
        more significant concern is that the scope of the issue if the query
        does leak, and the fact that this would then make the root of the
        alternate naming namespace a third level domain, and not a second one.
        A project may be willing to have a name of the form example.alt, but
        example.alt.arpa may be not look as good.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The IANA is requested to add the ALT string to the "Special-Use
      Domain Name" registry (<xref target="RFC6761"/>, and reference this
      document. In addition, the "Locally Served DNS Zones" (<xref
      target="RFC6303"/>) registry should be updated to reference this
      document.</t>

      <section title="Domain Name Reservation Considerations">
        <t>This section is to satisfy the requirement in Section 5 of
        RFC6761.</t>

        <t>The domain "alt.", and any names falling within ".alt.", are
        special in the following ways:<list style="numbers">
            <t>Human users are expected to know that strings that end in .alt
            behave differently to normal DNS names. Users are expected to have
            applications running on their machines that intercept strings of
            the form &lt;namespace&gt;.alt and perform special handing of
            them. If the user tries to resolve a name of the form
            &lt;namespace&gt;.alt without the &lt;namespace&gt; plugin
            installed, the request will leak into the DNS, and receive a
            negative response.</t>

            <t>Writers of application software that implement a non-DNS
            namespace are expected to intercept names of the form
            &lt;namespace&gt;.alt and perform application specific handing
            with them. Other applications are not intended to perform any
            special handing.</t>

            <t>In general, writers of name resolution APIs and libraries do
            not need to perform special handing of these names. If developers
            of other namespaces implement their namespace through a "shim" or
            library, they will need to intercept and perform their own
            handling.</t>

            <t>Caching DNS servers SHOULD recognize these names as special and
            SHOULD NOT, by default, attempt to look up NS records for them, or
            otherwise query authoritative DNS servers in an attempt to resolve
            these names. Instead, caching DNS servers SHOULD generate
            immediate negative responses for all such queries.</t>

            <t>Authoritative DNS servers SHOULD recognize these names as
            special and SHOULD, by default, generate immediate negative
            responses for all such queries, unless explicitly configured by
            the administrator to give positive answers for private-address
            reverse-mapping names.</t>

            <t>DNS server operators SHOULD be aware that queries for names
            ending in .alt are not DNS names, and were leaked into the DNS
            context (for example, by a missing browser plugin). This
            information may be useful for support or debugging purposes.</t>

            <t>DNS Registries/Registrars MUST NOT grant requests to register
            "alt" names in the normal way to any person or entity. These "alt"
            names are defined by protocol specification to be nonexistent, and
            they fall outside the set of names available for allocation by
            registries/registrars.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>One of the motivations for the creation of the alt pseudo-TLD is that
      unmanaged labels in the managed root name space are subject to
      unexpected takeover if the manager of the root name space decides to
      delegate the unmanaged label.</t>

      <t>The unmanaged and "registration not required" nature of labels
      beneath .alt provides the opportunity for an attacker to re-use the
      chosen label and thereby possibly compromise applications dependent on
      the special host name.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We would also like to thank Joe Abley, Mark Andrews, Marc Blanchet,
      John Bond, Stephane Bortzmeyer, David Cake, David Conrad, Patrik
      Faltstrom, Olafur Gudmundsson, Paul Hoffman, Joel Jaeggli, Ted Lemon,
      Edward Lewis, George Michaelson, Ed Pascoe, Arturo Servin, and Paul
      Vixie for feedback.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6761'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6303'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1034'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-terminology.xml'?>
    </references>

    <section title="Changes / Author Notes.">
      <t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this section before publication ]</t>

      <t>From -03 to -04:<list style="symbols">
          <t>3 changes - the day, the month and the year (a bump to keep
          alive).</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -02 to -03:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Incorporate suggestions from Stephane and Paul Hoffman.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -01 to -02:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Merged a bunch of changes from Paul Hoffman. Thanks for sending a
          git pull.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -00 to 01:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Removed the "delegated to new style AS112 servers" text -this was
          legacy from the omnicient AS112 days. (Joe Abley)</t>

          <t>Removed the "Advice to implemntors" section. This used to
          recommend that people used a subdomain of a domain in the DNS. It
          was pointed out that this breaks things badly if the domain
          expires.</t>

          <t>Added text about why we don't want to adminster a registry for
          ALT.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From Individual-06 to DNSOP-00<list style="symbols">
          <t>Nothing changed, simply renamed draft-wkumari-dnsop-alt-tld to
          draft-ietf-dnsop-alt-tld</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -05 to -06<list style="symbols">
          <t>Incorporated comments from a number of people, including a number
          of suggestion heard at the IETF meeting in Dallas, and the DNSOP
          Interim meeting in May, 2015.</t>

          <t>Removed the "Let's have an (optional) IANA registry for people to
          (opportinistically) register their string, if they want that option"
          stuff. It was, um, optional....</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -04 to -05</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Went through and made sure that I'd captured the feedback
          received.</t>

          <t>Comments from Ed Lewis.</t>

          <t>Filled in the "Domain Name Reservation Considerations" section of
          RFC6761.</t>

          <t>Removed examples from .Onion.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -03 to -04</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Incorporated some comments from Paul Hoffman</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -02 to -03</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>After discussions with chairs, made this much more generic (not
          purely non-DNS), and some cleanup.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -01 to -02</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Removed some fluffy wording, tightened up the language some.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -00 to -01.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Fixed the abstract.</t>

          <t>Recommended that folk root their non-DNS namespace under a DNS
          namespace that they control (Joe Abley)</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
